# 咱们放一个灵魂这也是关键
San-Bei Chicken
(featuring Thai Basil)
What we are putting in now is the soul of this dish
# 今天做一个三杯鸡
We are making San-Bei (three-cup) Chicken today
# 一杯麻油
One cup of sesame oil
# 一杯酱油
One cup of soysauce
# 一杯米酒
One cup of Chinese rice wine
# 然后这里边还有一个
And one more thing
# 最重要的最关键的
Which is also the most important
# 九层塔 也叫罗勒叶
Thai basil, one may use regular Basil
# 三杯鸡起源于江西
This dish originates from Jiangxi
# 真正盛行是在台湾
But got really popular in Taiwan
# 但是这个版本颇多
There are many different styles of this dish.
# 有不同版本的三杯鸡
Different ways to cook it.
# 你今天做什么版本的
How are you cooking it today?
# 今天我是这样
Here’s my plan
# 咱们做一个老饭骨邓氏的三杯鸡
I will do it in totally Lao Fan Gu style
# 咱们把化好的鸡腿切了
First, let’s chop the chicken thigh pieces
# 去骨么 不去骨
Debone it ? No we don’t debone it.
# 因为带骨煎出来鸡香
We need the bones for extra aroma
# 我是这么认为的骨头显着量大
I thought you keep the bones to make the portion look bigger.
# 肉带骨做出来它有骨香味
The bone gives extra flavour and aroma
# 这是肉鸡 这个是三黄鸡
Is this wild chicken? This is san-huang Chicken
# 现在都通称三黄鸡
A special breed of meat chicken
# 师父咱们切完了之后
After we are done with chopping
# 要在清水里头拔它一下
We need to rinse it in water
# 最好拔一小时以上拔透了
Better soak it for over one hour
# 这样做出来的鸡亮
Makes the chicken look cleaner after coocking
# 这鸡腌多长时间合适
How long should we marinate it?
# 咱们最好腌到一个小时以上
Preferably over one hour too.
# 一定要漂洗到没有血水
Rinse until all the blood is gone
# 然后挤净它然后再腌
Squeeze the excessive water out before marination.
# 这样煎出来的鸡清澈黄亮
So that the chicken will look clean and yellow after frying
# 洗的真干净
That’s clean
# 咱们腌这个鸡其中有一个
For the marination
# 我可能需要加的
I need to add one more thing
# 十三香 味道为王了么
the 13-spices, for the perfect flavour
# 最终是把味道做足
To maximise the flavour
# 三杯鸡的版本是按n次数算的
There are just so many different ways to cook this dish.
# 怎么做好吃咱就怎么来
As long as it tastes good.
# 然后师父还得加一点黄酒
Here, master, I will add some Huangjiu (yellow Chinese rice wine)
# 这个一定要腌入味
Marinate it through
# 酒香味出来了
You can smell the rice wine.
# 我跟你讲小邓
Let me tell you, Deng
# 你还记得咱们老厨房吗
Do you remember our old kitchen?
# 三十年前刚参加工作你一进厨房
Thirty years ago when you first started to work with me?
# 所有的菜的味道全是这个味道
The moment you start cooking, everything smells like this.
# 加一点酱油
A bit of Soysauce
# 要静置它一小时
Marinate for one hour
# 先搁这
Leave it here.
# 切点姜片 好了
Slice some ginger, alright
# 这里边从调料来讲
So, about the garnish.
# 最主要的还是蒜 要把蒜煸香
Garlic is the key, we will fry it to get the flavour out.
# 然后咱们再切点青红椒
Some red and green chilli pepper
# 主要是为了配色用
mainly for their colour
# 给我们兑这个三杯汁吧
Let’s make the sauce
# 第一杯我们要用麻油
First one is Ma You
# 麻油就是香油
Which is sesame oil
# 在台湾菜里边其实广泛用到了香油
It is very popular in Taiwan
# 而且它出来以后菜的味道确实很香
Also, the dish smells so much better with it.
# 我也借鉴了他一部分
So I learnt from it
# 一杯麻油
One cup of sesame oil
# 咱们今天用小碗了 三个小碗
We are using small bowls today. So three small bowls.
# 一杯米酒
One cup of rice wine
# 真正比例是
a good ratio is
# 香油3 米酒2 酱油1
Sesame : Rice Wine : Soy Sauce 3:2:1
# 然后我们加一杯（生抽） 差不多了
So lastly a cup of soy sauce.
# 如果说你生抽倒一 必定太咸了
It would be too salty if soy sauce is the same portion as others.
# 蚝油可以下上十五克到二十克
about 15-20 grams of oyster sauce
# 都没关系
Doesn’t really matter
# 最后这就是三杯
Here we have it, the three cups of sauce
# 香油提香
Sesame oil brings up the aroma
# 蚝油提鲜加味道
Oyster sauce boosts the umami
# 米酒去腥
Rice wine removes the unwanted smells of the meat
# 其实这个菜真正的东西它在这儿
That’s the main feature of this dish.
# 把它搁进去就是三杯鸡
What makes it the san-bei chicken
# 三杯鸡有各种的三杯的
The dish comes with different styles
# 凭你的口味去找你的口
Pick the favour you like the sauce
# 还是说一通百通用口味来变通
again, as long as you know the basic theory you can make your own combination.
# 咱下香油咱们先下一半
We will first use half of the sesame oil
# 现在是半杯
So half a cup now
# 放姜 把这姜煎成微黄
Slightly brown the ginger slices.
# 然后咱们下葱
Leek too.
# 把它的香气全面慢慢逼出来
Get the aroma out
# 逼到哪里呢逼到油里
And infuse the flavour to the oil.
# 小火慢煎
Low heat, fry slowly.
# 葱姜不炸永远不香 搁点蒜
Ginger and leek needs to be fried for the maximum flavour. Garlics in now.
# 咱们第二次把油下进去
Now we add the rest of the oil.
# 温度起来以后我们准备煎鸡
We fry the chicken when the temperature goes up.
# 三个鸡腿放这么多的葱姜蒜
All these for only three chicken leg pieces.
# 咱这个蒜子你看稍微有点微黄了
Garlic has been slightly browned.
# 下这个鸡
Put the chicken in.
# 可以把火开大一点没事没关系
The heat can go higher, that’s fine.
# 家里火还是慢 鸡肉有点出水
The heat at our home kitchen is still a bit weak, the moisture is coming out of the meat.
# 家里就这条件咱们火力不够
Well that’s the best we can do at home
# 这一面基本上颜色已经快变了
This side is getting some colour already.
# 下边又是葱姜蒜加上麻油
With all the leek, ginger and garlic frying in sesame oil
# 味道会浸入到整个的鸡肉里边
The flavour will go all they way through the meat
# 没错它能不香吗
No wonder it smells so good.
# 然后师父咱们现在开始放辣椒
Now we add the dried chilli pepper.
# 二荆条
The Er-Jing-Tiao chilli pepper
# 然后师父咱们现在该放第二杯了
OK master, now it’s time for the second cup.
# 米酒
Rice wine
# 有的地方会用什么样的米酒
People from different places use different rice wine
# 是用一种略甜的 对
Sometime they use a sweet type of rice wine.
# 师父咱们现在放第三杯
# Ok master, now it’s time for the third cup.
# 三杯鸡的任务陆续的往下投
We are completing the mission cup by cup.
# 欠一点黄
We need a little bit more colour.
# 再点一滴老抽 上上色
Some dark soy sauce for the colour.
# 放冰糖 十一二克
Crystal sugar, 11-12 grams.
# 再来一小把
A pinch more.
# 这个菜出来是咸甜还是甜咸
Is this dish mainly featuring sweetness or saltiness?
# 咸甜 就是咸压甜 对了
Salty, and a bit of sweetness.
# 好了师父咱们呢转进砂锅
OK master, now we move it into the clay pot.
# 转进砂锅慢慢焗
Cook it slowly in the clay pot.
# 把砂锅烧一下底
Let’s pre-heat the pot.
# 烧一烧然后把它挪过去
And then we pour the dish in.
# 烧热了砂锅里边不用垫点东西么
Do we need to put something in it when it’s hot?
# 不用 垫点儿羊肉
You know, something like lamb?
# 有酒用砂锅出的的香味浓
The rice wine elevates the flavour in the clay pot.
# 所以说一定要用砂锅 加盖
So we must use clay pot, with lid on.
# 歇一分钟收收汁
Let me take a break for a minute while it cooks.
# 这火合适
The heat is fine.
# 要有耐心
Be patient
# 想要吃好的味道一定要有耐心
It takes time to cook a proper dish and to achieve the desired flavour.
# 你看这就行了
Look, that’s almost done.
# 黏糊了
It’s getting thick
# 那么我们现在放点配色的
Now, it’s time for some colour in it.
# 咱们放一个灵魂这也是关键
And the one that brings soul to this dish.
# 这一下三杯鸡的特色一下出来了
Now that’s a proper san-bei chicken
# 没有它就是不行
You can’t cook a san-bei chicken without it.
# 亮师兄你看这鸡的颜色了吗
Liang, look at the colour of the chicken.
# 我看着呢我口水都要流出来了
I am, and it’s making me drool.
# 还有一个工序
One more step
# 我们把盖再盖上
Let’s put the lid back on.
# 这是师父教我的一个方式
I learnt it from my master.
# 围着这锅边 倒多少
Pour the wine around the lid. (How much?)
# 用砂锅的热气把黄酒的香气逼出来
Use the heat of the pot to get the aroma of the rice wine out.
# 走在路上这一道都是香的
The aroma will be so strong
# 上菜服务员都高兴
The waiter will be happy all the way serving it.
# 好了咱们现在关火了
OK let’s turn off the heat.
# 这香 你看这个
Smells amazing, look at it!
# 刚才加饭酒（黄酒）的味道了么
Smell that? The rice one I just added?
# 你闻一闻老冯
Smell this chef Feng.
# 我已经在这儿就闻到了
I smelt it already all the way from here.
# 就是这一路上
All the way from kitchen to the table
# 如果你要是在店里坐着
If you are sitting in the restaurant.
# 一路上都会有这个香味
You will smell it all the way.
# 可以开盖了整个挥发完
OK we can now open the lid.
# 香太香了
Smells amazing.
# 咱们别跟厨房吃了地儿小
Let’s not eat it here in the kitchen, it’s too crowded.
# 好菜不怕晚怎么样
A good dish is worth waiting for.
# 有点与众不同
Very unique
# 鸡香肉嫩
The chicken is very tender
# 有Q劲有弹性
Tender but still has its structure
# 有广东菜的特点
it has the features of a dish from Guagndong
# 也有台湾菜的特点
also that from Taiwan
# 还有小麻辣
Also, a little bit spicy.
# 好吃是王道
Anyway, most importantly it is delicious.
# 其实这是三杯鸡的灵魂
Now, this ingredient is the soul of this dish
# 叫罗勒叶
Thai basil
# 台湾还有一种叫法
In Taiwan people call it
# 叫九层塔
Jiu-Ceng-Ta
# 三杯鸡离不开九层塔
You can’t cook this dish without it.
# 这个菜红极一时 盛行一世
This was such a popular dish
# 所以说版本很多
That’s why there are many different variation of this dish.
# 好 吃吧
Alright, let’s dig in.
# 00:07:29 片尾开始